Guide to the Pavel Nikolaevich Shatilov Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Pavel Nikolaevich Shatilov Papers,
1921-1976
Shatilov, Pavel Nikolaevich
ca. 4,000 items (14 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY.
4078060
Biographical Note
Shatilov was chief of staff to General Petr Wrangel.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence and manuscripts. The correspondence, both incoming and outgoing (copies), spans the years 1921-1938, and includes both personal and official letters as well as such ancillary materials as financial accounts, reports, clippings, circulars, etc. It deals with the activities of the White army at the end of the Civil War (Crimea, Gallipoli, Bulgaria) and with the policies and programs of the Russkiĭ Obshche-Voinskiĭ Soiuz (ROVS) in the emigration. The manuscripts are in the form of memoirs, both General Shatilov's and his wife's; there is also a memoir by an unidentified author. There are two copies of General Shatilov's 2,000 page manuscript. In it he recounts his childhood and military education, his participation in the Russo-Japanese War, and his role in World War I, the Civil War, and subsequently in the emigration in Europe, through World War II.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Arranged Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts
Subjects
Soviet Union--History--Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Emigration and immigration--Soviet Union--20th century.; Emigration and immigration--Europe--20th century.; Russians--Europe.; Clippings.; Letters.; Memoirs.; Reports.
Access Restrictions
This collection has not restrictions
The collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1953 Papers Purchase
1977 Papers Purchase
- Series I: Arranged Correspondence
  This part of collection is not processed and currently unavailable due to preservation concern
  - Incoming: May-Dec. 1923 (Box 1)
  - Incoming: Jan.-Dec. ,1924 (Box 2)
  - Incoming: 1925 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re: to the transfer of Russian Army units, June 1921-Jan. 1922 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1921-1922 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Sofia with Sremskie Karlovtsy, Feb.-May 1922 (Box 4)
  - Outgoing: May-Dec. 1923 (Box 4)
  - Outgoing (personal): Jan.-Aug. 1924 (Box 4)
  - Outgoing (personal): May.-Dec. 1924 (Box 5)
  - Outgoing: 1925 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: 1926 (Box 5)
  - Personal Correspondence: 1927 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence re: the 10th anniversary of the White struggle, 1927 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: 1928-1929 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence re: the kidnapping of General Kutepov, 1930 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: 1930-1933 (Box 7)
  - Personal Correspondence: 1934-1935 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: 1936-1938 (Box 8)
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Subseries II.1: Shatilov's Manuscripts
    Subsiries consists of Memoirs (original typescript, transcript copy, and photocopy of transcript made in order to prevent usage of transcript due to its poor condition)
    - Sub-subseries II.1.1: Memoirs (original)
      Typescript with holographcorrections
      - Table of contents (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Detstvo i uchenie v Korpusakh (p. 1-68) (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Sluzhba v Leib Kazach'em Polku (p. 69-87) (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Akademiia General'nago Shtaba do Iaponskoi voiny (p. 88-95) (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Iaponskaia voina (pp. 96 - 226) (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
        [Do Liaoianskago srazheniia (pp. 96-150); Ot Liaoiana do Portsmutskago mira (pp.151-226)]
      - Akademiia posle Iaponskoi voiny (pp.227-263) (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Na Kavkaze do Velikoi voiny (p.264-317) (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Glavnoe Upravlenie General'nago Shtaba, 1914 god (p.318-326) (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Velikaia voina (pp. 327 - 502) (Box 9, Folder 10-13)
        [Peterburg. Shtab Iugo-Zapadnago fronta. 8-ia Kavaleriskaia diviziia. 1914 god (p.327-383a); V XVII korpuse i 7-i Kavaleriiskoi divizii. 1915 god (p.383b-432); Vo 2-i Kavkazskoi Kazach'ei divizii i v Shtabe armii. 1915 god (p.433-491); V Chernomorskom polku do revoliutsii. 1917 god (p.492-502)]
      - Fevral'skaia revoliutsiia (pp. 503 - 610A) (Box 9, Folder 14 - 17)
        [V Chernomorskom polku (p.503-535); Vystuplenie generala Kornilova (p.536- 561); Ot Kornilovskago vystupleniia do Brest-Litovskago mira (p.562-590); Ot Brest-Litovskago mira do prikhoda anglichan na Kavkaz (p.591-610a)]
      - Grazhdanskaia voina (610B - 896) (Box 9, Folder 18 - 24)
        [Ot zaniatiia Novorossiiska do operatsii protiv Chechni (p.610B-656A); Ot Velikokniazheskoi do vziatiia Tsaritsyna (p.656B-695); Ot Tsaritsyna do Tsaritsyna (p.696-754); Podavlenie metezha na Kubani i perevod v Dobrovol'cheskuiu Armiiu (p.755-789); Krushenie vlasti generala Denikina (p.790-843); Pervoe izgnanie (p.844-856); Krymskaia evakuatsiia(p.857-896) ]
      - Krymskii period bor'by na Iuge Rossii (additional text/insert - pp.899-1075) (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - V izgnanii: I. Bor'ba za sokhranenie Armii na chuzhbine (pp. 897 - 1075) (Box 10, Folder 2 - 9)
        [A. Razgruzka Armii i bezhentsev i pervye kontakty s frantsuzskim Komandovaniem (p.897-989); B. Rekonstruktsiia vlasti. Obrazovanie Komitetov v Parizhe i ikh otnoshenie k Armii (p.917-932); C. Perekhod flota v Bizertu (p.932-936); D. Bor'ba s frantsuzami za sokhranenie Armii (p.937-989); E. Zhizn' Armii, Shtaba i grazhdanskikh uchrezhdenii v lageriakh i v Konstantinopole (p.990-1020); F. Razryv s atamanami (p.1021-1050); G. Bor'ba s levoi obshchestvennost'iu i obrazovanie Russkago Soveta (p.1051-1066); H. Riad proektov ob ispol'zovanii Armii (p.1067-1075)]
      - V izgnanii: II. Razselenie Armii po Balkanskim stranam (pp.1076-1168): (Box 10, Folder 10)
        [A. Pervaia moia poezdka v Korolevstvo S.X.S i v Bolgariiu; B. Novye oslozhneniia s frantsuzami i ikh protivodeistvie nashemu planu razseleniia Armii; C. Otpravlenie pervykh partii v Serbiiu i v Bolgariiu; D. Novaia moia poezdka na Balkany i v Parizh; E. Zavershenie peregovorov po pereseleniiu Armii na Balkany ]
      - V izgnanii: III. Na Balkanakh (pp. 1169 - 1324) (Box 10, Folder 11 - 15)
        [A. Ustroistvo i zhiznennyia usloviia nashikh chastei na Balkanakh (p.1169-1201); B. Pereezd Vrangelia v Belgrad i oslozhneniia v Bolgarii. 1922 god (p.1202-1223); C. Delo Samokhvalova i vysylki iz Bolgarii (p.1224-1256); D. Mery priniatyia dlia paralizovaniia bolgarskikh nasilii (p.1257-1277); E. Nachalo dvizheniia v emigratsii i Armii v pol'zu priznaniia glavenstvaVelikago Kniazia Nikolaia Nikolaevicha (p.1278-1324) ]
      - V izgnanii: IV. Velikii Kniaz' vo glave Armii i natsional'nago dvizheniia (pp. 1325 - 1610) (Box 10, Folder 16 - 18)
        [A. 1923 god. Polnoe razvitie Nikolaevskago dvizheniia v emigratsii (p.1325-1390); B. 1924 god. Dvoistvennost' pozitsii Velikago Kniazia. Vystuplenie Imperatora. Priniatie Vel. Kniazem Nikolaem Nikolaevichem vysshego vozglavleniia Armiei i ofitserskimi soiuzami (p.1391-1452); C. 1925 i 1926 goda.Pervye rasporiazheniia Vel. Kniazia v otnoshenii Armii i zarubezhnyi s'ezd (p.1453-1529); D. Bor'ba Vrangelia za edinstvo zarubezhnago voinstva i ego konchina (p.1529-1573); E. Naznachenie Kutepova Predsedatelem ROVSa i ego pervye shagi i konchina Velikago Kniazia Nikolaia Nikolaevicha (p.1574-1610); ]
      - V izgnanii: V. Samostoiatel'noe vozglavlenie ROVSa generalami Kutepovym i Millerom (pp. 1611 - 1894) (Box 10, Folder 19 - 24)
        [A. Deiatel'nost' Kutepova v roli samostoiatel'nago vozglavitelia Russkago Obshche-Voinskago Soiuza (p.1611-1626); B. Pokhishchenie gen. Kutepova bol'shevikami (p.1627A-1678B); C: Vozglavlenie Millerom Obshche-Voinskago Soiuza. 1931 i 1932 goda (p.1679-1724); D. ROVS v 1933 i 1934 godakh do moei otstavki (p.1743-1811); E. Vozglavlenie i Otdela ROVSa gen. Erdeli i pokhishchenie gen. Millera (p.1812-1877); F. Sudebnoe sledstvie i protsess Plevitskoi (p.1878-1894)]
      - Vtoraia Mirovaia voina (pp. 1895 - 1973) (Box 10, Folder 25-26)
        [Do Obrazovaniia Vtorogo fronta (p.1895-1938); Obrazovanie Vtorogo fronta, osvobozhdenie Frantsii i polozhenie russkoi emigratsii (p.1939-1973)]
      - Prilozhenie: Letter of General Oprits (p.1974-1978) (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Sub-subseries II.1.2: Memoirs (transcript copy with holograph corrections)
      - Table of contents to Grazhdanskaia voina: Podavlenie miatezha na Kubani i perevod v Dobrovol'cheskuiu Armiiu (p.-831) (Box 11, Folder 1-21)
      - Grazhdanskaia voina: Krushenie vlasti generala Denikina (p. 832-) to V izgnanii: Velikii Kniaz' vo glave Armii i natsional'nago dvizheniia: 1925 i 1926 goda. Pervyia rasporiazheniia Velikago Kniazia v otnoshenii Armii i zarubezhnyi s'ezd (p.-1557) (Box 12, Folder 1-17)
      - V izgnanii: Velikii Kniaz' vo glave Armii i natsional'nago dvizheniia: Bor'ba Vrangelia za edinstvo zarubezhnago voinstva i ego konchina (p.1558-) to Prilozhenie: Pis'mo Gen. Opritsa po povodu klevetnicheskago vystupleniia G-zhi Denikinoi v gazete Novoe Russkoe Slovo (p.-2064) (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
    - Sub-subseries II.1.3: Memoirs (photocopy of transcript)
      - Table of contents to Grazhdanskaia voina: Podavlenie miatezha na Kubani i perevod v Dobrovol'cheskuiu Armiiu (p.-831) (Box 14, Folder 1-21)
      - Grazhdanskaia voina: Krushenie vlasti generala Denikina (p. 832-) to V izgnanii: Velikii Kniaz' vo glave Armii i natsional'nago dvizheniia: 1923 god.Polnoe razvitie Nikolaevskago dvizehniia v emigratsii (p.-1339) (Box 15, Folder 1-16)
      - V izgnanii: Velikii Kniaz' vo glave Armii i natsional'nago dvizheniia: 1924 god. Dvoistvennost' pozitsii Velikago Kniazia. Vystuplenie Imperatora i priniatie Velikim Kniazem Nikolaem Nikolaevichem vyshago vozglavleniia armiei i ofitserskimi soiuzami (p.1403) to Prilozhenie: Pis'mo Gen. Opritsa po povodu klevetnicheskago vystupleniia G-zhi Denikinoi v gazete Novoe Russkoe Slovo (p. 2064) (Box 16, Folder 1-12)
    - Sub-subseries II.1.4: Other Shatilov's Manuscripts
      - "Opisanie boevykh deistvii Armii Vooruzhennykh Sil Iuga Rossii za period s 27 Noiabria 1919 g. po 12 Marta 1920 goda." (typescript) (Box 16, Folder 13)
        [typescript]
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts by Others
    - Sub-subseries II.2.1: Shaposhnikov, Pavel
      - "Vospominaniia armeitsa: Irkutskoe Voennoe uchilishche" (Box 16, Folder 14)
        [34 pages of typescript with holograph corrections]
      - Related Materials: 2 Letters from Walter Peet to Pavel Shaposhnikov (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Sub-subseries II.2.2: Shatilova, S.F.
      - Vospominaniia (Box 16, Folder 16)
        [48 pages of typescript with manuscript corrections]